"Fecal Transplant Experiments Show the
Microbiome’s Role in the Aging Process"
Longevity researchers
have good reason to suspect
a causal
rather than bystander role
for age-related
microbiome changes.
A unifying theme
arising from some
of the best-studied models
of aging
is the central role
of the intestines
as a critical determinant
in lifespan.
In C. elegans,
the expression
of a longevity gene
in the animals’ nerves
produced a modest (10 percent)
life extension
and in their muscles
had no effect on lifespan
at all.
Expressed in their intestines,
however,
it increased lifespan
by 50 to 60 percent.
In fruit flies,
age-related changes
in their gut microbiomes
precedes a loss
of intestinal barrier function
that ultimately leads to death.
The lifespan
of individual flies
can be predicted
by this gut leakiness.
How do we know
their microbiomes
have anything to do with it?
Because if you give
10-day-old flies
the equivalent
of a fecal transplant
from a 30-day-old fly,
their young gut starts to leak,
and they die sooner
compared to getting microbiota
from another 10-day-old.
We suspect the driver is
the acquisition of bad bugs
from the older flies
rather than the loss
of good bugs,
since antibiotic treatment
significantly increases
their lifespan too.
Invertebrates are one thing.
What about an animal
with a backbone?
African turquoise killifish
are popular aging models
since they naturally
only live a few months,
allowing for rapid
experimental turnarounds.
What happens
when you recolonize the guts
of middle-aged fish
with bacteria
from younger fish?
They live longer lives.
They were also significantly
more active later in life,
in terms of spontaneous
exploratory behavior.
So, at least in the African
turquoise killifish,
age-related microbiome changes
appear not to just be
a passive consequence
of getting older,
but an active driver
of the aging process.
When they just gave antibiotics
to the middle-aged fish
to wipe out
their gut flora entirely,
they also lived longer,
suggesting bad bugs
were limiting their lifespan,
but they didn’t live as long
as the fish
transplanted
with the younger fish feces.
So there appeared to be
some salutary effect
of the good bugs of youth.
What happens
when you do the reverse
and give young fish
the microbiome of older fish?
Presumably they’d live
shorter lives, right?
But no, nothing happens.
That’s interesting.
The researchers suggest
that the lethal combination
is therefore
an aged immune system
facing an aged microbiome.
The young fish may be able
to handle the old microbiome
because its youthful
immune system
is able to reshape it.
What about in mammals?
The lifespan
of microbe-free mice,
those without
a gut microbiome at all
and raised under
germ-free conditions
like the "Bubble Boy,"
is increased
by up to 50 percent.
They appear to be protected
from inflamm-aging,
the rise
of systemic inflammation
as they get older.
Are gut bugs to blame
for this inflammatory increase?
Apparently so,
since compared
to feeding germ-free mice
poop from young mice,
old mouse poop caused
a leaky gut to develop,
bacteria toxins to spill
into the bloodstream,
and system-wide inflammation
to develop.
Fecal transplant studies
are how we can prove the role
of the gut microbiome
in disease processes.
If individual A
has disease X
and you can reliably cause
disease X
in healthy individual B
just by transferring
fecal matter
from the gut
of A to B,
then you can conclude
that the microbiome
plays a causal role
in the disease.
For ethical reasons,
these kinds of studies
aren’t performed in people.
All we can do is try to transfer
positive microbiome attributes.
How, then,
can we determine
if a disease state
is microbiome-related?
The most common approach
is to feed feces
from affected patients
to microbe-free mice
and see how they do compared
to microbe-free mice fed feces
from healthy people
as a control group.
There have been at least 38
such experiments published,
and 36 out of 38 (95 percent!)
found that the pathology could
be transferred through poop.
This was the case
even for conditions
not thought
to necessarily be gut related.
For example,
if you feed microbe-free mice
from the diaper of a baby
with a milk allergy,
the mice end up
with a milk allergy.
So maybe our gut microbiome
can help explain
why the prevalence
of food allergies
has been rising so much
in recent decades.
Regardless,
what about using this model
to explore the role
of our gut flora in aging?
Centenarian stool
has anti-aging effects
when fed to mice.
Researchers forced mice
to ingest fecal matter
from an elderly individual
(age 70),
which was found to contain
Bilophila wadsworthia,
a pro-inflammatory bacteria
enriched by a diet
high in animal products,
versus feces
from a 101-year-old
containing more fiber feeders.
Mice transplanted with
the centenarian microbiome
ended up displaying a range
of youthful
physiological indicators,
including less age pigment
in their brains.
This raises the possibility
that we will one day be using
centenarian fecal matter
to promote healthy aging.
Why bathe in the blood
of virgins
when you can dine on the dung
of the venerable?